P. Geoffrey Noyes Papers
P. Geoffrey Noyes Papers
1774-2005
1930-1970
Noyes, P. Geoffrey
12 linear ft
Genealogical and personal information on the Noyes family, founders of the Oneida Community; historical material concerning the Oneida Community and its commercial offspring, Oneida Community Ltd, manufacturer of silverware and china (among other things); and Noyes' correspondence with family and business associates.
2458297
Biographical History
P. Geoffrey Noyes was born June 16, 1941, at Oneida, New York. His great grandfather was John Humphrey Noyes, founder of the Oneida Community. His grandfather, Pierrepont Burt Noyes, and his father, Pierrepont Trowbridge (P.T. or Pete) Noyes, were chief executive officers of Oneida Community Ltd. and its successor companies. P. Geoffrey Noyes graduated from the Lawrenceville school in 1959 and Yale University in 1963. After military service, he worked for Oneida Silversmiths Ltd. until the mid 1980s.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The P. Geoffrey Noyes Papers span over one hundred years, with the bulk of the material from 1930-1970. The collection is divided into family material; material relating to the Oneida Community, a nineteenth-century utopian experiment founded by John Humphrey Noyes; and business-related papers and materials covering the transitional period when the Oneida Community became Oneida Community Ltd., commercial manufacturer of silverware and traps, through its post-World War II manufacturing as Oneida Ltd. Reflective of its time period, the collection includes corporate and personal responses to the Depression and World War II.
Family includes Noyes family genealogy and history as well as family correspondence. It also includes correspondence, notes and a libretto for an opera, "The Covenant," based on the communitarian philosophy of John Humphrey Noyes. Oneida Community encompasses historical material such as diaries of Humphrey Noyes and some personal reminiscences of Oneida Community members, information on Kenwood and the Mansion House, and some information on the Oneida Community’s views on plural marriage and relations between the sexes.
Oneida Community Ltd. includes company historical material, such as "A History of the Oneida Community Ltd." written by H.V. Noyes in 1930, early OCL constitutions and bylaws (which reflect their origins in the philosophy of the Oneida Community), and business procedures and instructions. There is significant correspondence of P. Geoffrey Noyes, his father Pierrepont Burt Noyes, his grandfather Pierrepont Trowbridge Noyes, and his uncle Miles E. Robertson. Because these individuals were family as well as business colleagues, the correspondence provides an unusually frank window into OCL corporate management relationships. Advertising includes catalogs, photographs and printed material as well as two market analysis reports which give insight into the relationship between marketing and social mores in the 1950s, particularly gender issues. There is information on sales agents, salaries, employee relations, and speeches given by Robertson and other company leaders (many of which demonstrate the persistence of the ideals of the Oneida Community). Financial and legal information includes an income tax statement from 1895, several account books belonging to Pierrepont Trowbridge Noyes, and trademark documentation. International operations covers OCL’s exploration of overseas business opportunities in Japan, Australia, Canada and the U.K. Stockholder communications includes, among other things, a near-complete run of the company’s annual reports, from 1895 to 2005. Artifacts and memorabilia include clippings, photographs, a miniature replica trap, and a sample case of stainless steel surgical instruments.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical. Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Related Material
See also the Oneida Community Collection.
Separated Material
A near-complete run of the company’s annual reports and a few other printed items have been removed from the collection and cataloged as part of the Rare Books Collection, as have two issues of Community Jeweler, OCL's trade/marketing journal. Please search using keyword "P. Geoffrey Noyes" to find these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Religion and Philosophy; New York State; Business and Industry; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965.; Devlin, Sean.; Klee-Hartzell, Marlyn.; Newhouse, S. (Sewell) -- How to catch wolves with the Newhouse wolf trap.; Noyes, P. Geoffrey.; Noyes, Pierrepont Trowbridge.; Noyes, Pierrepont, b. 1870.; Oneida Community.; Oneida, Ltd.; Animal traps -- History.; Collective settlements -- United States.; Family-owned business enterprises.; Flatware.; Intentional communities -- New York (State); Sales promotion.; Silverwork -- New York (State) -- Oneida.; Articles.; Business letters.; Corporation reports.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Genealogies (histories); Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Reviews (documents); Scrapbooks.; Sales catalogs.; Traps (trapping equipment); Businessmen
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of P. Geoffrey Noyes, 2006.
Inventory
- Collection inventories and correspondence
  - Inventories, P.Geoffrey Noyes, Jun 1992; annotated inventories created by the donor; outdated and no longer reflective of actual contents or arrangement of collection; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, correspondence concerning the collection (Box 1)
- Family
  - Biographical material
    - Genealogies, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-subject files
    - Family, misc., 1900-1941 (Box 1)
    - Baruch, Bernard M., 1931-1954 (Box 1)
    - Devlin, Sean, "The Covenant" (opera), notes and libretto; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Indenture, 1744 (Oversize 3)
    - Noyes, Pierrepont Burt, 8 folders (Box 2)
      See also Oneida Community Ltd.: Correspondence-subject files: Noyes, Pierrepont Burt
      Correspondence, one unidentified typescript, and reviews and letters relating to his books:
      Gentlemen, You Are Mad
      A Goodly Heritage
      My Father’s House
      The Pallid Giant
      Recollections of Oneida Community
    - [Pierrepont Burt] Noyes Memorial Fund (Box 2)
    - Noyes, P. Geoffrey, 1955-1963; 1963-1967,; 1999,; 2000; 3 folders (Box 2, 3)
      See also Oneida Community Ltd.: Correspondence-subject files: Noyes, P. Geoffrey
    - Noyes, Pierrepont Trowbridge (P.T.), 1941-1946; 2 folders (Box 3)
      See also Oneida Community Ltd.: Correspondence-subject files: Noyes, Pierrepont Trowbridge (P.T.)
    - Smith, Stella Worden, 1958-1963 (Box 3)
  - Memorabilia
    - Photographs (Box 3)
- Oneida Community
  - Correspondence-subject files
    - General, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Foster, Lawrence, articles on Oneida Community (Box 3)
    - Herrick, James Barton (Box 3)
    - Kenwood material, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Kinsley, Edith, article on Kenwood (Box 4)
    - Kirschner, Joseph, articles on Oneida Community (Box 4)
    - Klee-Hartzell, Marlyn (Box 4)
    - Mansion House, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities (Box 4)
    - Nelson, Truman (Box 4)
    - Noyes, Humphrey, includes his diaries, 1885-1886; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Olin, Spencer C., articles on Oneida Community (Box 4)
    - Plural marriage (Box 4)
    - "Records of Buildings" (Box 4)
    - "Two Sides of Heaven" (Box 5)
    - Woodrow Wilson Center (Washington, DC) (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Oneida Community Ltd.
  - Historical material
    - "A History of the Oneida Community Ltd." (H.V. Noyes), 1930; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Constitutions and bylaws (Box 5)
    - Instruction and policy manuals, 4 folders (Box 5, 6)
    - Scrapbook (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, photocopy of handwritten paragraphs about trap business funding silverware expansion, signed by "Steve"; photocopy of book chapter on Sewell Newhouse; mention of "Frank W-S" as steel consultant; other items (Box 6)
  - Correspondence-subject files
    - Austin, C.F. (Box 6)
    - Board of Directors (Box 6)
    - Hesper Silver Co. (Box 6)
    - "Magi Cup" (Box 6)
    - Noyes, G. W. (Box 6)
    - Noyes, H. H. (Box 6)
    - Noyes, Pierrepont Burt (Box 6)
      See also Family: Correspondence-subject files: Noyes, Pierrepont Burt
    - Noyes, P. Geoffrey (Box 7)
      See also Family: Correspondence-subject files: Noyes, P. Geoffrey
    - Noyes, Pierrepont Trowbridge (P.T.), 2 folders (Box 7)
      See also Family: Correspondence-subject files: Noyes, Pierrepont Trowbridge (P.T.)
    - Oneida Tower and Plaza (Box 7)
    - Project cards (Box 7)
    - Robertson, Miles E., 2 folders (Box 7)
    - [William A.] Rogers (Box 8)
      See also Oneida Community Ltd.: Business files: Financial and legal: Sales -- William A. Rogers
    - Sales Executive Club of Central New York (Box 8)
    - World War II production (Box 8)
    - Yahoo bulletin board postings (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Business files
    - Advertising
      - Photographs (Box 8)
      - Printed material (Box 8)
      - Radio (Box 8)
      - Stainless patterns (Box 8)
    - Catalogs
      - Chains, 1911-1912; No. 34-A, No. 35-C, No. 36-A (Box 16)
      - Hardware, 1901; 1904,; 1908-1909; No. 24a, No. 27a, No. 31a, No. 32a; includes traps and chains (Box 16)
      - Silverware, Wm. A. Rogers, 1908; No. 46 (Box 16)
      - Silverware, other companies, 1847; Rogers Bros. and Community Silver; numerous assorted small catalogs and price lists (Box 16)
      - Traps, Oneida, 1908; 1911-1912,; undated; No. 30A, No. 41, No. 42, No. 43, No. 44, No. 44-B; also several copies of "How to catch wolves with the Newhouse wolf trap" by Sewell Newhouse (Box 16)
      - Traps, other companies, 1908; undated; Animal Trap Co.; Blake, Lamb and Co.; The Hawkins Company (Box 16)
    - Employees
      - Benefits and stock purchase plans (Box 9)
      - Employee relations (Box 9)
      - "Labor Policy of Oneida Ltd." (Esther Lowenthal), 1927 (Box 9)
      - OCL Athletic Association (Box 9)
      - Sales agents (Box 9)
      - Talks to employees (Box 9)
    - Financial and legal
      - Account book, P.T. Noyes, 1908-1909? (Box 9)
      - Income tax, 1895 (Oversize 3)
      - Profit and Loss, P.T. Noyes, 1904-1921 (Box 9)
      - Salaries (Box 9)
      - Sales book, P.T. Noyes, 1880-1911 (Box 9)
      - Sales book, P.T. Noyes, 1881-1916 (Box 10)
      - Sales – Traps (Box 10)
      - Sales – William A. Rogers, 1928-1932 (Box 10)
        See also Oneida Community Ltd.: Correspondence-subject files: [William A.] Rogers
      - Stock offerings (Box 10)
      - Trademarks, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - International operations
      - International operations, pre-1972 (Box 10)
      - International operations, 1972-1973 (Box 11)
      - Japan, Australia, 1919 (Box 11)
      - United Kingdom, 1983; 1984 (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - Market analysis
      - Melamine dinnerware study, 1959; 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Silverplated flatware, 1914; 1937 (Box 11)
    - Stockholder communications
      - 1895-1938 (Box 12)
      - 1940-1948 (Box 12)
      - 1950-1969 (Box 12)
      - 1970-2005 (Box 13)
  - Memorabilia
    - Artifacts
      - 25th Anniversary Silversmith’s Race pins (2) (Box 14)
      - Sample case of surgical instruments (Box 14)
      - Trap (Box 14)
      - Trap, miniature replica (Box 14)
      - Turbine blade (Box 14)
    - Banquet menu/program, 2 Jan 1917 (Oversize 1)
    - Clippings (Box 15)
    - New York Stock Exchange (Box 15)
    - Photographs (Box 15)
    - Photographs (oversize) (Oversize 2)
    - Stock option poster, 1927 (Oversize 1)